<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="7"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[The net of a right circular cylinder consists of a rectangle and

                                             two circles. The length of the rectangle is equal to the
                                             circumference of the base, that is 2πr. Its width is the height
                                             of the cylinder h.



               Some useful formulas that are used in conjunction with  cylinders:
               •  The lateral surface area of a right circular cylinder is equal to the circumference of
                   the base times the height, h, of the cylinder: LA = 2πrh.
               •  The total surface area of a right circular cylinder is the sum of the lateral area and
                                                                                         2
                   twice the area, B, of one of the circles: TA = 2πrh + 2B = 2πrh + 2πr .
               •  The volume of a right circular cylinder is equal to the area of a base times the
                                                 2
                   height of the cylinder: V = πr h.

               Important
               The volume of a solid with the same cross-sectional area at all levels is the product of
               the area of the base and its height.
               The lateral surface area of a solid with the same cross-sectional area at all levels is the
               product of the perimeter of the base and its height.



                     p
                   m
                  a
               Example 3: Each base of the solid, shown to the right, is
               Examplee  3::
               E E x a m p l l e   3 :                                             16 cm         8 cm
                         3
                 x
                            formed by three semi-circles. The smallest
                            semi-circle of diameter 8 cm is removed from
                            the largest semi-circle. The bottom base sits
                            on a horizontal floor and the height of the                             20 cm
                            solid is vertical. Leave your answers in terms
                            of π.
                            a) Calculate the area of the base.
                            b) Calculate the volume of the solid.

                            c) Calculate the surface area of the solid.

                                                                  1      2           2
                                                                     (

                  l
                  l
                  u
                    t
                  u
               S S
               Solution: a) The area of the largest semi-circle is  π 12 ) = 72  cm .
               Solution:
                o
                o
                    t
                     i
                       n
                     o
                       n
                     o
                        :
                     i
                        :
                                                                                π
                                                                  2
                                                                   1     2           2
                             The area of the middle semi-circle is  π ( ) =8  32 π  cm .
                                                                   2
                                                                    1     2
                                                                                     2
                             The area of the smallest semi-circle is  π ( ) = π4  8  cm .
                                                                    2
                                                                              2
                             The area of the base is 72π + 32π − 8π = 96π cm .
                                                                               3
                          b) The volume of the solid is 96π × 20 = 1,920π cm .
                          c) The perimeter of the base is (24π + 16π + 8π) ÷ 2 = 24π cm.
                                                                                        2
                             The lateral surface area of the solid is 24π × 20 = 480π cm .
                                                                                             2
                             The total surface area of the solid is 480π + 2 × 96π = 672π cm .

               Mathematical Studies 2                  142                            Chapter 6: Mensuration]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[直圆柱体的立方体展开图包含一个矩形和两个圆形。矩形的长度等
                                             于底面的周长，即  。它的宽度是圆柱体的高度 。







               与圆柱体相关的一些实用公式：
                  直圆柱体的侧表面积等于底面周长乘以圆柱体的高度 ：                                    。
                  直圆柱体的总表面积是侧面积和其中一个圆形面积                           的两倍之和：
                                                。

                  直圆柱体的体积等于底面面积乘以圆柱体的高：                               。


               重要提示
               在所有层面上具有相同横截面积的立方体的体积是底面面积和其高度的乘积。

               在所有层面上具有相同横截面积的立方体的侧表面积是底面周长和其高度的乘积。



               例     右图中立方体的每个底面由三个半圆组成。在最大半圆中
                     有一个直径            的最小半圆。底部底面位于水平面上，
                     立方体的高度是垂直的。保留答案中的。
                        计算底面积。

                        计算立方体的体积。
                        计算立方体的表面积。







               解      最大半圆的面积为                        。

                      第二大半圆的面积为                        。


                      最小半圆的面积为                      。


                      底面积为                            。

                      立方体的体积为                              。
                      底面周长为                                  。
                      立方体的侧表面积为                              。

                      立方体的总表面积为                                    。













               数学研究                                    142                              第五章：乘积法]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[i
                      i
                      v
                      v
                    c
                    c
                     t
                     t
                         y
                         y
                           3

                        i
                        i
                        t
                        t
                  A A
                  Activity 3                                                                        2 m
                  Activity  33
                  The figure to the right shows a trough. Its bases are
                  semi-circles of radius 0.4 m. Its length is 2 m. Give all
                                                                                                         0.4 m
                  answers to two decimal places.

                  a) How many cubic meters of water are needed to fill the trough?
                  b) After being filled with water, a hole was discovered at the bottom of the trough.
                     How many hours does it take the hole to drain the trough if it is leaking at the rate
                     of 0.5 liters per minute?


                   L L e a r n i i n g     P o i i n t t   4
                   Learning Point 4
                     a
                          n
                   Learning Point  44
                       n
                               o
                      r
                                 n
                             P
                    e
                           g
                   Apply the surface area and volume of a cone.
                   Concepts 10 - 12

                  Cones
                  C C o n e s
                      e
                  Coness
                    o
                     n
                  A cone is a solid geometric figure whose base is a circle.                  V
                  Its lateral face is a curved surface which tapers from the
                  circular base to a point, called the apex of the cone. Its
                  radius, r, is the radius of its base and its height, h, is the   Slant height, l   h
                  distance from the apex to the center of the base. The
                  slant height, l, of a right cone is the distance from the
                  vertex to any point on the circumference of the base.                          r
                  The surface of the cone excluding the base is called the                   O
                  lateral surface.

                  Some useful formulas that are used in conjunction with cones:
                  •  The lateral surface area of a right circular cone is LA = πrl.
                  •  The total surface area of a right circular cone is the sum of the lateral surface area
                                                             2
                      and the area of the base: TA = πrl + πr .
                                                                 1
                                                                     2
                  •  The volume of a right circular cone is V =    πr h.
                                                                 3
                        p
                          e
                            4
                      m
                     a
                   x
                  Example 4: Sector ACB is centered at C and its radius is 10 cm.
                  E E x a m p l l e     4 : :                                                   C
                  Example 4:
                               CA  and CB  are joined to form a cone.
                                                                                                60°
                               a) Calculate the radius of the cone.                                 10 cm
                               b) Calculate the volume of the cone.
                               c) Calculate the surface area of the cone.                A              B




                  S S
                       t
                     l
                   o
                  Solution:
                     u
                     u
                     l
                   o
                       t
                          n
                          n
                           :
                           :
                  Solution: a) The circumference of the base is the length of arc AB
                        i
                       i
                        o
                        o
                                          60            10 π
                                which is      × π×10  =      cm.
                                         180             3                                    h     10 cm
                                The radius of the cone is the radius of its base.
                                    Circumference      10 π / 3  5
                                It is                =        =    cm.                            5/3 cm
                                           2 π           2 π    3


                  Mathematical Studies 2               143                               Chapter 6: Mensuration]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[练习
                  右图是一个水槽。它的底面是半径为                         的半圆。长度为
                      。所有答案精确到小数点后两位。




                     填充水槽需要多少立方米的水？
                     装满水后，在水槽底部发现一个小孔。如果水槽以每分钟                                升的速度漏水，需要多少小时
                     才能通过这个小孔排空内部的水？


                   知识点
                   运用圆锥体的表面积和体积。
                   概念

                  圆锥体
                  圆锥体是底面为圆形的立体几何图形。它的侧面是一个曲面，
                  从圆形底面逐渐缩小为一个点，称为圆锥体的顶点。它的半径
                  是它底面的半径，它的高度                是从顶点到底面中心的距离。直                   斜高
                  圆锥体的斜高 是从顶点到底面周长上任何一点的距离。除了
                  底面之外的圆锥体表面叫做侧表面。









                  与圆锥体相关的一些实用公式：
                     直圆锥体的侧表面积为                  。
                     直圆锥体的总表面积是侧表面积和底面面积的总和：                                    。

                     直圆锥体的体积为                   。


                  例    扇形        的中心为 ，半径为                 。
                            和    相连形成圆锥体。                                                         
                          计算圆锥体的半径。
                           计算圆锥体的体积。
                          计算圆锥体的表面积。




                  解     底面的周长是圆弧             的长度，即：
                                          
                                            。

                        圆锥体的半径就是它底面的半径。
                                         
                                                  。
                                       










                  数学研究                                 143                                 第五章：乘积法]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[b) The height of the cone is given by
                                              2
                             h = 10  2  −  (5 / 3 ) = 875 / 9  ≈ 9.86 cm.
                             The volume of the cone is, approximately,
                             1                 2
                                                            3
                               π× 9.86  ×  (5 / 3 ) ≈ 28.68 cm .
                             3
                                                                                              2
                          c) The lateral surface area of the cone is π × (5/3) × 10 ≈ 52.36 cm .
                                                                         2
                                                              2
                             The area of the base is π × (5/3)  ≈ 8.73 cm .
                             The surface area of the cone is, approximately,
                                                      2
                             52.36 + 8.73 = 61.09 cm .

                   i
                   i
                    v
                    v
                 c
                 c
                  t
                  t
                     i

                      y
                        4

                     t
                     i
                      y
                      t
               Activity 4
               A A
               Activity 44
                                                                                        8 cm
               A small cone of slant height 8 cm is removed from a                   h
               bigger cone. The bases of the two cones are parallel. The
               radius of the bigger cone is 5 cm.                                            4 cm
               Give all answers to two decimal places.
               a) Find the volume of the remaining solid.                               5 cm

               b) Find the surface area, including both bases, of the remaining solid.


                          P
                          P

                       n
                       n
                      i

                        g
                        g
                            o
                               t
                               t
                                 5

                              n
                             i
                            o
                              n
                             i
                Learning Point 5
                Learning Point  55
                  a
                    r
                     n
                     n
                    r
                 e
                      i
                 e
                  a
                L L
                Apply the surface area and volume of a sphere.
                Concepts 13 - 14

                  h
                   e
                p
                  h
                     e
                     e
                   e
                       s
               Spheress
               S S
                     r
                p
                    r
               Spheres
               A sphere is the set of points in space at a given distance from
               a fixed point. The fixed point is the center of the sphere and
               the given distance is the radius of the sphere.
                                                                                              r
                                                                                         O
               If a sphere is cut by a plane into two equal parts then each
               part is called a hemisphere.

               Some useful formulas that are used in conjunction with spheres:
                                                   4
                                                       3
               •  The volume of a sphere is V =      πr .
                                                   3
                                                          2
               •  The surface area of a sphere is S = 4πr .
                                                               2   3
               Consequently, the volume of a hemisphere is  πr , the surface area of the curved
                                                               3
                                           2
               part of a hemisphere is 2πr , and the (total) surface area of a hemisphere is
                   2     2       2
               2πr  + πr  = 3πr .
               Mathematical Studies 2                  144                            Chapter 6: Mensuration]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[圆锥的高度由下式得来：
                                                           。

                       圆锥体的体积约为                                    。

                       圆锥体的侧表面积为                                 。
                      底面积为                       。

                      圆锥体的表面积约为                                     。

               练习
               较大圆锥体中有一个斜高为                    的小型圆锥体。这两个圆锥
               体的底面相互平行。较大圆锥体的半径为                          。
               答案精确到小数点后两位。
                  求阴影立方体的体积。

                  求阴影立方体（包括上下两个底面）的表面积。



                知识点
                运用球体的表面积和体积。
                概念


               球体
               球体是在空间中距离固定点给定距离处的点集。固定点是球体的中
               心，给定距离是球体的半径。

               如果一个球体被一个平面切割成两个相等的部分，则每个部分就叫
               做半球。





               与球体相关的一些实用公式：

                  球体的体积是                。

                  球体的表面积是                。

               因此，半球的体积是               ，半球曲面部分的表面积为                  ，半球的（总）表面积是

                               。






















               数学研究                                    144                              第五章：乘积法]]></page></pages></Search>