<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="7"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[C a b e z a   d e   V a c a


















                                                   PART TWO:


                              THE WANDERER AND THE HEALER






























                                                            61]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[C a b e z a   d e   V a c a





                                    Alvar did not know what to do.  For hours, he rested in

                             the shade.  He did not even have enough energy to search for

                             water or food.  Suddenly, he noticed something move in the

                             bushes at the other end of the beach.  When he looked up, he
                             saw a man squatting with a bow and arrows in his hands.  The

                             man had light brown skin, short hair, and a bone pierced

                             through his upper lip like a thin moustache.  Alvar was too

                             tired to be scared.  He looked at the man and did not move.

                                    Soon, a large group had gathered to stare at Alvar, all
                             of them with similarly pierced lips and weapons.  Alvar had

                             seen many strange things and new people during the past

                             months, but he was the first European these natives had ever

                             seen.  He realized they were probably more curious about him

                             than he was about them.
                                    ‘I must be the strangest thing they have ever seen,’

                             Alvar thought.  ‘Skinny as a skeleton, and sunburned as red as

                             a crab.’

                                    After a while, several women approached Alvar.  They

                             placed bowls of food and water in the sand a few feet from
                             him.  The women watched in amazement as Alvar scrambled



                                                            63]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[C a b e z a   d e   V a c a



                           toward the bowls as if he was trying to attack them.  He ate

                           and drank everything they had brought.  Alvar had no idea

                           what he was eating, and he did not care how it tasted.  The

                           natives smiled and brought more food and water.

                                  Alvar was so busy eating that he did not notice the
                           natives coming closer and closer, until they were gathered in a

                           circle around him.  When he finished everything, he moaned

                           and rolled over on his side.  After so many weeks of hunger,

                           he had eaten too much too fast.  Alvar fell into a deep sleep,

                           and when he awoke, he was in a small, dark hut, wrapped in
                           animal skins.  He heard people singing and drumming outside.

                           When he lifted the flap of deer hide that covered the door, he

                           saw many people dancing around a huge bonfire.  He closed

                           the flap and crawled back into bed, and shivered with fear.

                                  ‘Oh no!’ he thought.  ‘I have heard stories of wild
                           dances and bonfires.  The Indians are going to eat me!’

                                  All of the stories about tribes of cannibals, and the

                           terrible things they did to Conquistadors in Mexico and other

                           places, filled Alvar’s head.  He did not know what to do.  Just

                           when he made up his mind to escape, however, the deer hide
                           flap lifted up.  Alvar made himself as small as possible



                                                           64]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[C a b e z a   d e   V a c a



                             beneath the blankets.  When he peeked at the door, he saw a

                             man covered from head to toe in red paint with raccoon fur

                             wrapped around his head.  His chest, face, and arms were

                             pierced with many thin bones.  The man walked across the hut

                             and pulled Alvar’s blankets away.
                                    “No!  Please don’t eat me!” Alvar screamed.

                                    The man called to someone else outside.  A woman

                             came in with a jug of water and knelt beside Alvar.  Using a

                             soft rag, she sponged water onto his face and hands, then

                             poured some over his hair.  Alvar looked at the woman’s face.
                             She would not look into his eyes, but he knew as he watched

                             her wash him that he was not in danger.  He felt like a fool for

                             having been so afraid.  ‘These people are not cannibals,’ he

                             thought.  ‘They saved my life.’

                                    Alvar was allowed to stay in the natives’ village, and as
                             the weeks passed he learned a lot about the people and their

                             way of life.  They called themselves Capoques, and Alvar was

                             able to learn their language.  As it turned out, the man who

                             had been painted in red dye during the bonfire took Alvar into

                             his own home.  His name was Flies With Hawk, because
                             when he was a child he fell from a tall tree and was not hurt.



                                                            65]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[C a b e z a   d e   V a c a



                           His wife, who had washed Alvar, was named Fighting Wind,

                           because she had been born during a bad hurricane.  Alvar was

                           glad that, like all of the Capoques, his own name had special

                           meaning.  The Capoques listened carefully to his story of why

                           he was named ‘Cabeza de Vaca,’ unlike the governor and
                           most other people Alvar had known.

                                  They lived on an island not far from the mainland, but

                           only in the winter.  It was hard to find food in the winter, and

                           the Capoques were not a powerful tribe.  This island was the

                           only place the Capoques could find food where they would
                           not have to fight other tribes.  Alvar called this the Isle of

                           Misfortune because life was so hard here.

                                  Their main food was roots, which they boiled and

                           mashed into a soupy mixture with a little fish, or whatever

                           else they could find.  Each day Alvar joined the Capoques in
                           the shallows of the creeks and sea where they gathered roots,

                           because the ground above water was too frozen to dig.  The

                           more time Alvar spent with them, the more surprised he was

                           by their customs.

                                  He had never met people who loved their children
                           more than the Capoques.  As a child in Spain, Alvar had been



                                                           66]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[C a b e z a   d e   V a c a



                             taught to respect, and even to fear his parents and other elders,

                             and certainly never to question them.  Capoque parents were

                             very tender and loving, which was nothing like what he

                             expected from people who were supposedly savage.  Until

                             they were twelve years old, and big enough to work, the
                             children were free to play and explore their world.  Life was

                             not easy on the Isle of Misfortune, but hearing the laughter

                             and playful cries of the children each day made everything a

                             little better.

                                    During the winter several children fell ill and died.
                             When this happened, the whole tribe joined the family in

                             mourning the loss.  Each day at dawn, and then again at noon,

                             the parents and relatives of the dead child would cover

                             themselves in ash from the fire and cry for an hour.  They

                             continued this for a whole year.  The rest of the tribe would
                             give the family food, because people in mourning were not

                             allowed to gather their own.  Of course, this made everything

                             more difficult for the Capoques, because it meant fewer hands

                             were available to dig roots.

                                    The winter was cold, and everyone was hungry and
                             sick.  Most of the people got better, but Alvar was not used to



                                                            67]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[C a b e z a   d e   V a c a



                           the germs, and his body did not recover quickly.  Every night

                           he would lie awake sweating, wild with fever.  At the same

                           time, he felt cold, and horrible chills swept through his body.

                           He grew even thinner, and his skin took on a yellowish color.

                           None of the Capoque healers were able to help him.
                                  “Cabeza de Vaca?  Can you hear me?  It is Flies With

                           Hawk.  Wake up, Cabeza de Vaca.”

                                  “I am cold,” Alvar groaned.  “Will you build up the

                           fire?”

                                  “The fire is burning.  Stay still and rest,” Flies With
                           Hawk said, wiping the sweat from Alvar’s brow.  “I have

                           come to tell you that the rest of us are going to the mainland

                           because winter is over.  It is time to eat oysters and

                           blackberries.  You must stay here.  You are too weak to travel.

                           Do not worry, Cabeza de Vaca.  You will not be alone.”
                                  The words faded from Alvar’s mind, and everything

                           became dim.



                                                    *      *      *







                                                           68]]></page></pages></Search>