<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Search><pages Count="23"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

                                          The Age of Exploration


                  When did the Age of Exploration begin and why?

                                                         The Age of Exploration started in the 1400s.
                                                         Europeans were trying to find new trade routes
                                                         to the Far East from where they imported silk
                                                         and spices, valuable commodities at the time.
                                                         Silk was used to make fine clothing and spices
                                                         kept food from spoiling. Europeans had so far
                                                         relied on the Silk Road, a long and dangerous
                                                         route linking Europe with China. The rulers of
                  Europe started to fund explorations to find new sea routes to Asia.

                  Which countries were involved in the exploration?

                                                         Portugal  was  the  first  European  country  that
                                                         sent explorers to search for new ways to reach
                                                         China.  However,  other  countries  quickly
                                                         followed  and  competition  soon  started
                                                         between  European  neighbors.  Christopher
                                                         Columbus wanted to find a shortcut to China
                                                         by sailing west. When Portugal refused to fund
                                                         his  trip,  he  went  to  the  rulers  of  Spain,  who
                                                         gave  him  money.  His  discovery  of  a  new
                  continent  on  this  now  legendary  trip  brought  glory  to  Spain.  Other  European
                  countries  such  as  France,  England,  and  Holland  later  joined  the  competition  to
                  conquer new lands in the New World.

                  Who are the most famous European explorers? What did they discover?

                                                         Italian-born Christopher Columbus sailed west
                                                         from Spain in 1492 on an expedition funded by
                                                         the king and queen of Spain. After a long and
                                                         difficult  journey,  he  arrived  at  the  island  of
                                                         Hispañola. Thinking he was near the coast of
                                                         China,  he  named  the  Caribbean  islands  the
                                                         West Indies. Columbus claimed the new lands
                                                         he  discovered  for  Spain.  He  never  reached
                                                         mainland  North  and  South  America,  which
                                                         were later discovered by a flurry of explorers
                                                         who followed him to the New World.








                                                                                                         1]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

                                   Vasco Da Gama was a Portuguese explorer who sailed to India
                                   by going around Africa. He was the first to navigate a sea-route
                                   from Europe to India. In 1497, he sailed from Portugal, rounded
                                   the Cape of Good Hope in South Africa, and went on to India. It
                                   took ten months to complete his journey.




                                   Ferdinand Magellan was another explorer from Portugal. Instead
                                   of heading east like other explorers, Magellan tried to reach the
                                   Far East by sailing west around South America. He left Spain in
                                   1519 with nearly 250 men and four ships. Three years later, only
                                   one  ship  returned  carrying  18  men.  Magellan  was  not  one  of
                                   them.  Although  the  trip  cost  him  his  life,  Magellan  became
                                   famous as the first explorer to sail around the world.

               Which civilizations lived in the New World?

                                                     Great  civilizations  and  empires  thrived  in  the
                                                     New  World.  Among  them  were  the  Aztecs  of
                                                     present-day  Mexico  and  the  Incas  of  the
                                                     country  of  Peru.  These  two  peoples  led  an
                                                     advanced  way  of  life  which  ended  abruptly
                                                     after  they  were  conquered  by  Europe.  The
                                                     Aztecs were formidable engineers. They built a
                                                     magnificent  capital,  Tenochtitlan,  which  was
               larger than any European city at the time. The Incas built a complex road system
               and created new agricultural methods including terraced farming.

































               2]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

                  Pre-Reading

                  Useful links:

                  http://www.pbs.org/weta/thewest/people/a c/cabezadevaca.htm
                  Biography from the PBS series The West.
                  http://www.vaca.com/cabeza.html
                  Includes an in depth coverage of Cabeza de Vaca’s journey.
                  Make sure to explore all the links within the website.
                  http://www.library.txstate.edu/swwc/cdv/
                  Includes an online copy of de Cabeza Vaca’s book “La Relacion”
                  http://www.mariner.org/exploration/index.php?type=explorer&id=67
                  Has information on explorers’ routes, ships and the navigation tools they used.
                  http://www.archaeolink.com/explorer_panfilo_de_narvaez.htm
                  Includes several links with information on the Narvaez expedition.
                  http://www.eldritchpress.org/cdv/rel.htm#c11
                  An analysis of Cabeza de Vaca and his journey.
                  http://www.pbs.org/conquistadors/devaca/ devaca_a00.html
                  From the PBS documentary Conquistadors.

                  History

                  Alvar Nunez Cabeza de Vaca (1490-1557) was a Spanish explorer well-known for
                  the years he spent living with the Natives in the American southwest.
                  He was born into a noble family and most of his ancestors were warriors. His name,
                  Cabeza de Vaca, translates into "Head of a Cow." The Spanish king gave the title to
                  one of Cabeza de Vaca’s ancestors after he helped Spain win a battle by marking a
                  difficult trail with cow skulls. Cabeza de Vaca also distinguished himself as a fine
                  officer in the king’s army.
                  In 1527, he was appointed Treasurer of the Panfilo de Narvaez expedition and sailed
                  to America looking for riches. The expedition ran into many difficulties, including
                  storms,  attacks  by  the  natives,  and  starvation.  After  a  shipwreck  on  the  Isle  of
                  Misfortune, off the coast of the Gulf of Mexico, he spent nearly ten  years living
                  with Native American tribes. At first, he was treated as a slave but then he acquired
                  skills as a trader and healer, giving him a special status among the tribes. He spent
                  many years alone among the Natives before meeting up with four other survivors of
                  the expedition. The group then ran into Spanish soldiers stationed near Culiacàn,
                  Mexico, from where they made their way back to Spain.
                  Cabeza  de  Vaca  later  wrote  a  chronicle  about  his  adventures  in  the  New  World
                  called Relaciòn. This enlightened account, in which he appeals for better treatment
                  of the Natives, is considered the earliest description of the Native American way of
                  life before it was destroyed by colonization. He describes the customs and traditions
                  of dozens of tribes which have since been wiped out. Upon his return to Spain, he
                  was appointed Governor of Rio de la Plata in South America.
                  However, he soon fell out of favor with the king because of his sympathetic views
                  toward the Natives. He was banished to Africa, but is believed to have returned to
                  Spain where he died in 1557.


                                                                                                         3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

               Introducing the Reader

                   1.  When did the age of exploration begin? What made people want to explore?








                   2.  What is a trade route? Give an example.








                   3.  Which European countries were involved in exploration?








                   4.  Name three explorers and identify their most famous discoveries.









                   5.  Who lived in the New World?



















               4]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

                      6.  What shows that the people of the New World were advanced?


















































































                                                                                                         5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

               Vocabulary (pages 3-6)
               Context clues

               Context  clues  help  readers  figure  out  the  meaning  of  unknown  words.  Read  the
               sentences carefully and underline the clues that help you understand the meaning of
               the word in bold. Next, write a definition of the word in bold using the words that
               you have underlined.

                   1.  On a snowy day, people should be careful and drive with extreme caution.

                       caution:

                   2.  The  rainforest  is  home  to  a  large  variety  of  exotic  birds.  They  are
                      distinguished by their unique and unusual colors.

                       exotic:

                   3.  My greatest achievement today was cleaning up my room. I managed to tidy
                      up in less than two hours.

                       achievement:

                   4.  Before I knew Elsa, I had a negative opinion of her, but now I think she is
                      not so bad.

                       negative:

                   5.  As we were driving along the coast we saw endless groves of  citrus trees
                      bearing oranges, tangerines, and lemons.

                       citrus:

                   6.  Food cooked without the right combination of spices is flavorless and does
                      not taste good.

                       spice:

                   7.  In my opinion, the former coach of Germany’s soccer team was much better
                      than the present one.

                       former:











               6]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

                  Biography
                  Hernando Cortes (page 5)

                  Hernando Cortes  (1485-1587)  was the Spanish explorer who became famous for
                  leading the expedition that started the conquest of Mexico. He was part of the first
                  generation of European explorers who began the colonization of the New World.
                  The  gold  and  riches  that  he  discovered  in  the  Aztec  empire  inspired  many  other
                  explorers to follow his steps.
                  In  1519,  leading  a  small  force,  Cortes  peacefully  entered  the  Aztec  capital  of
                  Tenochtitlan, rich in gold and other treasures. The Aztecs soon rebelled against the
                  Spanish presence, but their revolt was brutally crushed. Cortes quickly became a
                  hero in Spain because of the riches he sent home. As a reward, the king of Spain
                  appointed  Cortes  governor  of  Mexico.  However,  the  king  became  suspicious  of
                  Cortes’  ambitions  and  sent  officials  to  Mexico  to  investigate  his  actions  and
                  ruthlessness toward the Natives. In 1528, Cortes was ordered to return to Spain. He
                  was  later  sent  back  to  Mexico  but  was  never  reappointed  governor.  He  died  in
                  Spain in 1587.

                      1.  Which civilization in the New World did Cortes encounter in his conquests?



                      2.  Why did other explorers want to follow in his footsteps?



                      3.  How did Cortes and his men treat the Aztecs?




                      4.  Why was Cortes ordered to return to Spain? Give two reasons.



























                                                                                                         7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

               Comprehension (pages 3-6)

                   1.  Who was Alvar? What country was he from? What century did he live in?
                      What was his family background?








                   2.  How did Alvar’s sense of adventure grow from when he was a child until he
                      became a Conquistador?





                   3.  How large was the expedition and who was its leader?






                   4.  Historical  context  gives  information  about  what  was  happening  during  the
                      time that the story took place.

                      Do the following sentences give information about the historical context of
                      Alvar’s expedition?

                      - Ships sailing to the New World stopped in the Canary Islands.         Yes/No

                      - Conquistadors were hoping to find great riches in the New World.  Yes/No

                      - The men were enthusiastic about the expedition.                       Yes/No

                      - Many Conquistadors considered Hernan Cortes a hero.                   Yes/No

                   5.  Why was the king of Spain angry at Cortes?



                   6.  Why did Narvaez dislike Cortes?








               8]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

                  Vocabulary (pages 7-12)


                  Choose the best word to fit the sentence. Remember to look for context clues to help
                  you choose the correct answer.

                      1.  Samir always ________when                  3.  My sister and I share a small
                         he buys a new video game. He                    room. I sometimes feel
                         announces it to the entire class.               ________ for space.

                         [-A-] claims                                    [-A-] cramped
                         [-B-] ignores                                   [-B-] experienced
                         [-C-] boasts                                    [-C-] unguarded
                         [-D-] explores                                  [-D-] damaged
                         [-E-] launches                                  [-E-] invested

                      2.  We sat out on the balcony and              4.  The supermarket offered great
                         contemplated the sun as it set in               _________ to its frequent
                         the distant _________.                          shoppers.

                         [-A-] deck                                      [-A-] judgments
                         [-B-] horizon                                   [-B-] plains
                         [-C-] colony                                    [-C-] skulls
                         [-D-] haze                                      [-D-] complaints
                         [-E-] landmass                                  [-E-] rewards







































                                                                                                         9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

               Comprehension (pages 7-12)

                   1.  Why was Alvar worried about the Governor’s desire to compete with Cortes?





                   2.  Authors use foreshadowing clues to make readers wonder what will happen
                      next in a story. What does the following passage foreshadow?
                      ‘After all we are going somewhere that no Spaniard has ever been. There is
                      no way of knowing what dangers await us in Florida.’

                      [-A-] The expedition will find gold in Florida.
                      [-B-] Spaniards have never been to Florida.
                      [-C-] The expedition may run into trouble in Florida.
                      [-D-] It will take a long time to reach Florida.
                      [-E-] Governor Narvaez is very greedy.

                   3.  What factors slowed down the ships?




                   4.  ‘The more we suffer, the greater our rewards...’
                      What conclusions can you make about Narvaez’s character from this
                      statement?







                   5.  Name some of the problems that the expedition ran into at this early stage of
                      the journey. Do you think this is a sign of things yet to come?















               10]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

                      6.  How did Alvar comfort himself while the expedition was facing problems?



















































































                                                                                                        11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

               Vocabulary (pages 13-16)
               Compound words

               Compound words are two or more words joined together to form a new word.
               market+place = marketplace                            gang+plank = gangplank

               A. Read the sentences below. Create compound words by choosing words from the
                   list to fill in the blanks.

                   powder        back       bow         shop      land       smith

                   1.  Horse_____ riding is my favorite hobby.

                   2.  In the old days, every village used to have at least one black_____.

                   3.  My aunt has her own work_____ where she designs and produces beautiful
                      scarves.

                   4.  When we went to Greece, we visited the islands but not the main_____.

                   5.  Gun_____ was invented in China.

                   6.  A cross_____ is a weapon which was used hundreds of years ago.

               B.  Use the following words to create compound words.

                   fisher, spring, foot, deer, man, print, skin, salt, water, time

                   _______         _______        _______         _______         _______
































               12]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

                  Geography
                  Hispañola (page 13)

                  In  1492,  Christopher  Columbus  discovered  the  island  of  Hispañola,  the  second
                  largest in the Caribbean, on his voyage to the New World. It was inhabited by a
                  group of Taino Indians who were peaceful and friendly to Columbus and his crew.
                  In the following years, Europeans started establishing settlements on the island. The
                  most important colony was the city of Santo Domingo which was founded in 1496
                  by  Bartholomew  Columbus,  Christopher’s  brother.  The  island,  whose  Taino
                  population  was  wiped  out  over  the  next  twenty-five  years,  became  a  base  for
                  explorers looking for new lands in the Caribbean and mainland America.
                  The island was later divided into two sides. One was controlled by the French and
                  the other by the Spanish. The French side is now known as Haiti and the Spanish
                  side has become the Dominican Republic.

                      1.  Which explorer discovered Hispañola? In what year?



                      2.  The Natives who lived on Hispañola were ___________:

                         [-A-] violent
                         [-B-] welcoming
                         [-C-] explorers
                         [-D-] Spanish
                         [-E-] French


                      3.  What happened to the island’s native population?




                       4.  Why was Hispañola important to explorers?






                       5.  What is Hispañola known as today?











                                                                                                        13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

               History
               The Horse and the Conquest of the New World (page 15)

               The  Natives  did  not  have  horses.  They  had  never  seen  this  animal  until  the
               Conquistadors brought it to the New World in the 16th century. The trip across the
               Atlantic was not always easy for horses. They were the first to suffer when water
               and food supplies were low on the ships. Some were tossed overboard.
               The Conquistadors quickly established farms in the New World to breed horses that
               they  used  during  their  conquest  wars.  When  the  Natives  first  saw  the  bearded
               Spaniards wearing helmets and breastplates and riding horses, they were frightened
               to death.
               The horse was later adopted by many tribes and became an important part of their
               culture.

                   1.  Who introduced the horse to America? When?




                   2.  Why were horses a necessity for Conquistadors?




                   3.  How did the Natives react when they first saw Conquistadors riding horses?




                   4.  How did the Natives benefit from the introduction of the horse to the New
                      World?































               14]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

                  Comprehension (pages 13-16)

                      1.  Describe Santo Domingo. Give details from the text.












                      2.  Why did Narvaez and his men stop in Santo Domingo?




                      3.  Why were horses important to the Narvaez expedition?






                      4.  Do you think the musket was a practical weapon for the Conquistadors to
                         use? Why?






                      5.  Why did the Conquistadors carry muskets if they were not practical?






                      6.  Narvaez picked up all of the following items in Hispañola except:

                         [-A-] weapons and horses
                         [-B-] a large bell
                         [-C-] a small boat
                         [-D-] gold and silver
                         [-E-] food and supplies





                                                                                                        15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

               Vocabulary (pages 17-22)

               Choose the best word to fit the sentence. Remember to look for context clues to help
               you choose the correct answer.

                   1.  My father’s business did well this year. He will make good __________.

                      [-A-] deserts
                      [-B-] services

                      [-C-] profits
                      [-D-] residents
                      [-E-] anchors

                   2.  Most shops that sell large items like furniture keep their goods in a
                      __________.

                      [-A-] fountain
                      [-B-] warehouse
                      [-C-] barrel
                      [-D-] navigator
                      [-E-] canoe

                   3.  __________ my bag quickly, I ran out of the house to catch the school bus.

                      [-A-] grabbing
                      [-B-] grinned
                      [-C-] deserted
                      [-D-] rowed
                      [-E-] paddled

                   4.  The bus driver __________ us that we would arrive home by 5:30.

                      [-A-] supposed
                      [-B-] discussed
                      [-C-] assured

                      [-D-] gritted
                      [-E-] guided













               16]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

                  Literature
                  Foreshadowing (pages 17-22)

                      1.  Authors use foreshadowing clues to make readers wonder what will happen
                         next in a story.

                         A. Which of the following sentences is a foreshadowing clue?

                         [-A-] On the way to Florida, the Narvaez expedition made several stops on
                         the island of Cuba.
                         [-B-] ‘You should sail to Florida as soon as possible before the weather
                         changes.’
                         [-C-] ‘What is the pay for a navigator on your expedition?’

                         [-D-] Alvar was made captain of the small ship Narvaez bought in Hispañola.
                         [-E-] ‘Are there good harbors for the ships?’

                      B. What does the sentence foreshadow?





                      2.  Authors sometimes use their description of the weather to warn of a possible
                         disaster.

                      A. Which of the following descriptions foreshadows danger?

                         [-A-] Huge storm clouds began to darken the sky.

                         [-B-] The wind blew furiously.
                         [-C-] Rain came pouring.
                         [-D-] The sea began to churn.
                         [-E-] all of the above

                      B.  Write  one  more  sentence  describing  the  weather.  Make  sure  it  also
                         foreshadows danger.
















                                                                                                        17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

               Comprehension (pages 17-22)

                   1.  Why was Narvaez angry?





                   2.  Why did many of the men desert?





                   3.  What did Governor Narvaez think about the deserters?





                   4.  ‘Governor  Narvaez  met  a  rich  man  named  Vasco  Porcallo,  who  owned
                      warehouses  full  of  food  and  other  supplies  in  the  small  town  of  Trinidad.
                      These he offered to the expedition in return for some of the gold Narvaez
                      promised they would find.’
                      What does the pronoun ‘these’ refer to?

                      [-A-] Trinidad
                      [-B-] warehouses
                      [-C-] supplies
                      [-D-] gold
                      [-E-] Vasco de Porcallo

                   5.  A  character  motivation  is  the  reason  why  a  character  acts  or  thinks  in  a
                      certain way. To find a character’s motivation always ask ‘why?’
                      Why did Miruelo boast about his knowledge of the waters around Florida?



                   6.  Trinidad  was  a  dangerous  place  to  stop  for  two  reasons.  What  are  these
                      reasons?

                      [-A-] It was too far and too small.
                      [-B-] It was inhabited by cannibals and savage beasts.
                      [-C-] It had no harbor and the weather was changing.

                      [-D-] It had no water or supplies.
                      [-E-] all of the above



               18]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

                  Journal (page 22)

                  In this journal, you will make a list of Alvar’s character traits which will help you
                  complete the writing exercise at the end of the reader. Character traits describe a
                  person’s personality, feelings or thoughts.
                  In their writing, authors sometimes use exact words to describe a character. Other
                  times, they describe them through their actions, thoughts or feelings.


                  Read the following passage and answer the questions below.

                         “Señor Cabeza de Vaca,” one of the men shouted as a wave drenched the
                  canoe, “the master of the plantation insists that you come out of this awful weather
                  and join him for dinner.”

                         “Tell him ‘thank you,’ but that I am used to bad weather. Besides, I am
                  responsible for these ships and crews.”
                  “Please, señor, we have a horse for you on shore. You will be quite pleased with the
                  supplies we have to offer.”
                         Alvar could see that the men in the canoe were not going to give up, so he
                  decided to go along with them.  Alvar invited the other men on the ship, but they all

                  said ‘no,’ except Miruelo.

                      Why did Alvar hesitate before leaving his men on the boat?






                      What conclusions can you make about Alvar’s character based on his actions?



























                                                                                                        19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

               Independent Activity
               Hurricanes (page 21)

               The storm that the expedition ran into was a hurricane, which is a type of tropical
               storm  that  forms  over  the  Atlantic  or  eastern  Pacific.  This  rotating  storm,  with
               winds  over  74  miles  (119km)  per  hour  is  also  called  a  typhoon  in  the  western
               Pacific, and a cyclone in the Indian Ocean.

               Research this topic online and bring in information to share with the class. Some
               interesting  aspects  to  cover  are:  What  is  a  hurricane?  How  does  it  form?  What
               damage can it inflict? How does one survive a hurricane? What are some famous
               hurricanes?

               http://www.kidinfo.com/science/weather.html
               http://42explore.com/hurricane.htm
               http://environment.nationalgeographic.com/environment/natural-disasters/
               forces-of-nature/


               You can spin your own hurricane on the National Geographic website.

















































               20]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

                  Vocabulary (pages 23-29)

                  Write a word from the box to replace the underlined words or phrases.

                   splinter                     blinked                       motionless
                   puddles                      huddled                       confidently
                   slammed                      overpower                     loaned

                      1.  The racket flew out of my hand and hit violently against the window.



                      2.  I shut and opened my eyes several times to adjust to the bright lights.



                      3.  After it rained, we ran to the yard to jump into the pools of water.



                      4.  The boy hid in the closet where he stayed without moving.



                      5.  My cats crowded together next to the fire to stay warm.




                      6.  I admire my sister because she always speaks as if she is sure of herself.




                      7.  It was painful when a sharp piece of wood became stuck under my fingernail.



                      8.  Alex gave me her book temporarily so I could read it over the weekend.













                                                                                                        21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

               Geography
               Expedition Trail (page 29)

               Narvaez and his men landed near Tampa Bay on the west coast of Florida. Find the
               location on the map. Continue to follow the expedition trail as the story develops.




































               Independent Activity
               Explorers’ Ships (page 27)

               You can research this subject online and produce an annotated drawing with basic
               information about life on an explorer’s ship.


















               www.abc.net.au/navigators/ships/investigator.htm
               Has an excellent interactive tour of a ship.






               22]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Cabeza de Vaca Exercise Book

                  Comprehension (pages 23-29)

                      1.  In the passage “On the shore…in the church” the author uses action verbs to
                         describe  the  violence  of  the  storm.  These  verbs  show  the  reader  what
                         happened so that they can visualize the action. Find the action verbs in the
                         passage and write them down.



                      2.  Suspense is a feeling of uncertainty or excitement. Authors use suspense to
                         make the reader more interested in the story.
                         Find and copy three sentences on page 24 that create suspense about what
                         happened to the missing boat and its crew.

                         a.

                         b.

                         c.

                      3.  What were the losses  that the expedition suffered during the storm?  Find
                         three details in the passage.




                      4.  How did the Conquistadors make up for some of their losses during their stay
                         in Santiago?



                      5.  Explain how a ship can get stuck on a sandbar.






                      6.  How many hurricanes did the men survive after they sailed for Florida?



                      7.  What was the first thing Narvaez intended to do when he landed in Florida?







                                                                                                        23]]></page></pages></Search>
